Guide to the University of Chicago Department of Anthropology Records 1929-1997
University of Chicago Library
University of Chicago. Department of Anthropology. Records
1929-1997
73 linear feet (146 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
The Department of Anthropology at the University of Chicago was founded in 1929 under the chairmanship of Fay-Cooper Cole. The collection comprises records of the department from its inception through 1997. It includes the Fay-Cooper Cole Papers, information and data from early archeological, linguistic and socio-cultural anthropological fieldwork, early materials on teaching and curriculum, files on department buildings and space, administrative and financial papers and documentation, faculty and staff information and student files.
Information on Use
Access
Series VII: Administration contains central administrative files from the Department of Anthropology, Division of Social Sciences, Collegiate Division and University Administrations. These are subject to 30-year restriction (R-30).
Series VIII: Faculty and Staff contains salary and budgetary information, as well as information related to hiring practices and is restricted for 50 years from the date of creation (R-50).
Series IX: Finance contains long-term budget information and information on invidual student and faculty grants and are therefore restricted for 50 years from the date of creation (R-50).
Series X: Student Files, contains evaluative student material including grades, exam scores, and recommendation letters and must be restricted for 80 years (R-80) from their date of creation.
The remainder of the collection is open for research.
Historical Note
The Department of Anthropology at the University of Chicago was founded in 1929 under the chairmanship of Fay-Cooper Cole, but had a longer historical presence at the University. Anthropology was established as a field of early interest at the University of Chicago through William Rainey Harper's appointment in 1892 [the first year that classes were held] of Frederick Starr as the first faculty member in anthropology. This was one of Harper's first acts as the inaugural president of the University of Chicago.
Starr was originally appointed into the "scientific department", but with Harper's development of the "social science" (or sociology) department under Albion W. Small, he was quickly reappointed. During the period of his appointment until his retirement in 1923, Professor Starr frequently traveled, conducting research in the United States and Mexico, as well as in Japan, Korea, the Philippines and Africa. Starr was an immensely popular teacher and lecturer, but his frequent travels regularly interrupted instruction in anthropology, necessitating the continued administrative integration of Anthropology with the department of Sociology.
Following Starr's retirement, the University offered a part-time appointment to Fay-Cooper Cole, who had done long-term fieldwork in the Philippines in 1906, and was employed at the Field Museum. Cole consolidated his position, lobbied for and achieved the separation between the departments of sociology and anthropology in 1929, and facilitated the recruitment and appointment of the brilliant linguistic anthropologist Edward Sapir, a second-generation student of Franz Boas who helped to shift the intellectual culture of the department away from Starr's museum orientation to the knowledge of the patterns of social behavior, and especially of symbolism. Sapir's influence inspired linguistic anthropological fieldwork by Manuel Andrade, Harry Hoijer and Father Bernard Haile amongst various communities in the United States and Mexico.
Sapir's appointment was followed shortly by that of Robert Redfield, whose policy-orientation towards contemporary America and interest and concern with contemporary social issues reveals the influence on the department of anthropology of the Chicago School of Sociology and its chair, Robert E. Park (who was also Redfield's teacher and father in law). Redfield and Tax's early research on rural and urban communities in Yucatan (and subsequently Guatemala) further articulated this influence. In addition to small portions here, larger collections on this research can be found in the papers of Robert Redfield and Sol Tax as well as the papers of the Chiapas Project.
Early research also included the archeological excavation of important sites in Illinois, including the Kincaid Mounds, which for many years served as a summer "field school" for anthropology graduate students and a key site where modern archeological field methods were developed and revolutionized. This research revealed how certain archeological features in these sites established the state of Illinois as central in the understanding of the etho-history of the Mississippi Valley region. The department produced various monographs and a comparative pictorial survey (conducted primarily by Thorne Deuel) of the archeology of the region.
A significant moment in early departmental history was the initially temporary appointment of British social-anthropologist Alfred Reginald Radcliffe-Brown to the faculty to replace Sapir's initially temporary position at Yale. Radcliffe Brown's reworking of Durkheimian themes in his ahistorical approach to social structure and function reoriented the department towards the "social science" from which it had since departed. This perspective contrasted sharply with Sapir's historically particularist Boasian framework, resulting in a revealing schism between the "socially" and "culturally" oriented anthropologists in the department. Both their respective "temporary" appointments became permanent, until Radcliffe-Brown's departure for Oxford in 1937 and Sapir's death in 1939.
In the late 1950's the recruitment of Lloyd Fallers, Clifford Geertz and David Schneider from the University of California Berkeley breathed new life into the department following the death of Redfield (of Leukemia in 1958) and the departure of Sherwood Washburn and Lloyd Warner. These former three scholars reoriented the department towards a symbolic approach to anthropology, which had a monumental impact on the field. These young scholars also oriented the department towards the ongoing recruitment of "star" anthropologists who would revolutionize the field. The personal and professional papers of these three scholars are all available for research in the University of Chicago Library, Special Collections Research Center.
Subsequent faculty hires with a significant impact on the culture, research and ongoing influence of the department of anthropology include Marshall Sahlins, Bernard Cohn, Michael Silverstein, Jean and John Comaroff, Terence Turner, Stanley Tambiah, Nancy Munn, Valerio Valeri and George Stocking. These scholars have all further articulated the themes that have long concerned Chicago anthropologists with increased attention to the relationship between anthropology and history, colonialism and imperialism and semiotic approaches to culture. Rooted in these historical and contemporary influences, the University of Chicago's Department of Anthropology has continued to be one of the premier departments in anthropological instruction and research in the world.
Scope Note
The records of the University of Chicago Department of Anthropology include materials from 1929 when the Department was founded as a distinct entity under the Chairmanship of Fay-Cooper Cole until 1996. Periods in this timeframe are unevenly represented with the bulk of materials from the 1960's to 1996.
Series I: Fay-Cooper Cole Papers includes the professional papers of Professor Fay-Cooper Cole. This alphabetically ordered series incorporates Cole's professional correspondence with fellow professors, university administrators, professional organizations, anthropological institutions and funding agencies, as well as his graduate students' field reports.
Series II: Research is divided into four subseries documenting a range of early research activities carried out by the Department of anthropology. Subseries 1 contains the correspondence and research materials of the Committee on the Ethnohistory of the Upper Mississippi River Valley. Subseries 2 incorporates field reports and correspondence relating to summer archeological research conducted primarily at Kincaid Mounds, but also at other sites throughout the region and the country. Subseries 3 contains miscellaneous research materials and correspondence relating to the archaeological research conducted in the department of anthropology.
Subseries 4 includes correspondence, field materials, interview transcripts, surveys and field notebooks from the Winnebago/Ho-Chunk research of Rachel Commons and Leo Srole. [Commons died of Pneumonia with her Winnebago research incomplete. Srole was later sent to pick up where she left off, the field materials in subseries four are the partial result of that enterprise. Other materials relating to Commons/Srole can be found in Fay-Cooper Cole's correspondence in Series I.]
Series III: Alphabetical files incorporates three alphabetically ordered subseries that represent the administrative papers and departmental correspondence from the period following Fay-Cooper Cole's retirement, though it most fully represents the years between 1950 and 1970. This series most likely corresponds to the period in which Robert Redfield and Fred Eggan alternated as chair of the Department, with Sol Tax also periodically holding the position. The series is divided into three subseries.
Subseries 1: Correspondence incorporates alphabetically filed departmental correspondence from 1950-1956. Subseries 2: General Alphabetical Files, incorporates the administrative correspondence of the department with various institutions, other universities and funding agencies. Subseries 3: Wenner-Gren Symposium on Graduate PhD Curricula holds the contributions of various anthropology departments from across the country to a 1958 Wenner Gren conference on Anthropological PhD curricula.
Series IV: Microfilm includes a collection of departmental microfilms pertaining to various fields of research. Subseries 1 contains microfilm pertaining to Chiapas and the University of Chicago Chiapas Project. Subseries 2 contains materials on Guatemala.
Subseries 3 incorporates materials from Sol Tax's Research on the Fox and Sauk native American tribes in Tama, Iowa, and some subsidiary materials. Subseries 4 incorporates materials pertaining to linguistic and socio-cultural research on India. Subseries 5 includes miscellaneous and/or unlabeled microfilm materials.
Series V: Buildings and Space incorporates correspondence, surveys, architectural plans and information pertaining to the maintenance of, allocation to and movement from various campus buildings. The bulk of material involves the Walker Museum and Haskell Hall. Also of interest are materials relating to the procurement and installation of the Totem Pole in Haskell Hall.
Series VI: Teaching incorporates syllabi, teaching statements and curricula for undergraduate and graduate courses in anthropology. Most of these materials pertain to required anthropology courses.
Series VII: Administration incorporates in a single chronologically-organized series the Department's internal administrative files as well as those concerning the department's connection to the Division of Social Sciences, the College and the central University administration. As these materials are central administrative papers, they are subject to restriction for 30 years from their date of production. Their organization into a single chronological sequence facilitates research by allowing researchers to access earlier files while later files are still subject to restriction. These papers date from 1934 to 1997.
Series VIII: Faculty and Staff consists of a single chronologically-organized series of files pertaining to faculty and staff recruitment, salary information and correspondence. As these files contain data of a financial and budgetary nature, they are subject to a 50 year financial restriction from the date of their production. This series has been organized chronologically so researchers may access the earlier files while the later files remain under restriction. The dates of these files span from 1938 to 1991.
Series IX: Finance consists of six subseries that incorporate departmental financial materials. Because of the financial and budgetary nature of the materials in this series, they are subject to a 50-year financial restriction from the date of their production. Subseries 1: Departmental Budgets incorporates departmental budgets and accounting information from 1939-1986. Subseries 2-5 include materials related to various private and government granting agencies. Subseries 6: Miscellaneous Finance incorporates miscellaneous materials relating to departmental expenditures, including departmental luncheon invoices and expense accounts.
Series X: Students incorporates five subseries concerning the students in the Department of Anthropology. Subseries 1: Student Files is comprised of student files which may include grades, correspondence, financial information and admission information for students. Subseries 2: Exams includes original copies of official student departmental examinations as well as faculty commentary and grades for the exams. Subseries 3: Grades includes grade sheets and reports from the registrar's office, as well as individual term papers and class rosters that include student evaluative material. Subseries 4: Awards and Aid includes reports and evaluations and allocations of student funding and recommendations and nominations for student awards and membership in honor societies such as Sigma Xi and Phi Beta Kappa. Subseries 5: Jobs and Recommendations includes correspondence and faculty recommendations for department students for jobs at other universities.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
Cole, Fay-Cooper, b. 1881; Commons, Rachel; Radcliffe-Brown, A.R, 1881-1955; Redfield, Robert, 1897-1958; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939; Srole, Leo; University of Chicago. Department. of Anthropology; Illinois State Museum; Laboratory of Anthropology (Museum of New Mexico); Illinois State Academy of Science; Anthropology -- Study and teaching (Higher); Anthropology -- United States; Excavations (Archaeology) -- Illinois
INVENTORY
- Series I: Fay-Cooper Cole Papers
  - American Anthropological Association I, 1931-1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Anthropological Association II, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Anthropological Association III, 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Anthropological Association IV, 1940-1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Andrade, M. J., 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Barker, George (including field notes on language use and assimilation by Mexican Americans), 1943-1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Barker, George, 1942-1946 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bowers, A. W. (including field correspondence from work done among Hidatsa and Mandan in South Dakota, 1933), 1933-1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bowers, A.W. 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Buitron, Anibal (correspondence and field reports from Quiroga, Ecuador), 1945 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Buitron, Anibal, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Buitron, Anibal (field report to the government of Ecuador, in Spanish), 1946 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - C, Miscellaneous, 1931-1946 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Carnegie Institution, 1934-1943 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Chicago Anthropological Society, Bulletin of (v.1, nos. 1-4, 1945), 1945 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Cole, Fay-Cooper: Personal, 1941-1946 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Cole, Fay-Cooper: Divisional lectures, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Cole, Fay-Cooper: Publications, reviews, speeches, 1928-1932, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Cole, Fay-Cooper: Publications, Reviews, Speeches, 1931-1944, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Cole, Fay-Cooper: Lecture engagements, vitae, 1935-1947 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Commons, Rachel (correspondence about field work among the Winnebago of Wisconsin, 1932-35), 1932-1935 See also Series II, Subseries IV (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Cooper, Arch Elredge (including field work done in Accompong, Jamaica, 1939), 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Cornelius, Julius R. (World's Fair Investment, 1934), 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Cressman, L.S., 1943-1947 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Curriculum, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - E, Miscellaneous, 1939-1947 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Eggan, Fred, 1941,1945, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Embree, John (Japan), 1936, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - F, Miscellaneous, 1930-1947 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Fellowships and Scholarships, Committee on, 1933-1935 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Fellowships and Scholarships, Committee on, 1929-1933 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Field Museum of Natural History, 1930-1947 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Fuller, Anne (including field correspondence from Lebanon, 1938), 1937-1938 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - G, Miscellaneous, 1942-1946 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - G, Miscellaneous, 1937-1944 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Gilbert, W. H. (including field correspondence about Eastern Cherokee, 1932), 1932-1940 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Griffin, James, 1931-1947 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - H, Miscellaneous, 1942-1947 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - H, Miscellaneous, 1926-1944 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Haile, Father Berard: Research in Athabascan ethnology and linguistics, 1930's (includes letters from Edward Sapir on Navajo material), 1930-1946 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Haile, Father Berard: Flintway, 1939-1944 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Halpern, Abe (including field correspondence about Pomo and Yuma languages, circa 1935, 1940), 1939-1940, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Hawley, Florence (including correspondence on dendro-chronology), undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Hawley, Florence, 1934-1939 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Hawley, Florence, 1939-1943 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Herskovits, M. J., 1934-1946 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Heyerdahl, Thor, 1940, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Hoijer, Harry, 1932-1947 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Humanities Project #19: American Indian Languages, 1930-1931 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Hutchins, R.M., 1930 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - I, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Illinois State Academy of Science, 1939-1944 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Illinois State Academy of Science, 1934-1938 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Indian Affairs Office, John Collier, 1934-1945 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Indian Affairs Office, John Collier, 1934-1935 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Inquiries, 1944-1946 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - International Institute of African Languages and Cultures, 1929-1934 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - J, Miscellaneous, 1932-1942 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Jacobson, Edward, 1936-1939 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Jennings, Jesse, 1936-1941 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - K, Miscellaneous, 1929-1942 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - K, Miscellaneous, 1929-1947 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Kelly, A. R., 1929-1934 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Kidder, A. V., 1929-1946 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - King, Fain, 1936-1942 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Kroeber, Alfred, 1929-1945 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Krogman, Wilton, 1931-1944 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Krogman, Wilton, 1920-1930 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - L, Miscellaneous, 1939-1959 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - L, Miscellaneous, 1928-1939 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Laboratory of Anthropology, Santa Fe, New Mexico: Correspondence I, 1939-1946 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Laboratory of Anthropology, Santa Fe, New Mexico: Correspondence II, 1934-1939 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Laboratory of Anthropology, Santa Fe, New Mexico: Correspondence III, 1929-1933 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Laboratory of Anthropology, Santa Fe, New Mexico: Correspondence IV, 1935-1936 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Laboratory of Anthropology, Santa Fe, New Mexico: Correspondence V, 1937-1939 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Laboratory of Anthropology, Santa Fe, New Mexico: Miscellaneous reports, 1936-1941 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Laboratory of Anthropology, Santa Fe, New Mexico: Minutes summer session of Board of Trustees, July 8-9, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Laboratory of Anthropology: Report of the Director, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Laboratory of Anthropology: Report of the Director, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Laboratory of Anthropology: Survey of the Laboratory, Oct. 1938 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Laboratory of Anthropology: Report of the Director, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Laboratory of Anthropology: 1939 Public Relations Plan Memorandum (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Laing, Cordon (Editor of the United Education, Inc.), 1944-1945 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Langford, George (McKenna Process Co.), 1931-1947 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Langford, George (McKenna Process Co.), 1928-1930 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Lectures, student (arranged through the Anthropological Speakers Bureau to Combat Nazi Racism), 1940-1943 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Lessa, William, 1942 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Library (recommended purchases and list of those to receive archaeological, ethnological and linguistic series), 1931, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Lilly, Eli, 1939-1945 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Linton, Ralph, 1919, 1935-1942 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Local Community Research Committee: Charles Blooah, 1928-1933 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Local Community Research Committee: Sapir, Personality Research, 1930 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Local Community Research Committee: Indian Trails Project by Dena Shapiro, 1928-1929 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Locke, Alain, 1929 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Logan, Frank, 1928-1946 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Mc, Miscellaneous, 1938-1942 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Mc, Miscellaneous, 1935-1942 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - McAllister, J.G. 1930-1946 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - McKern, W. C. (Milwaukee Public Museum),1939-1942 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - M, Miscellaneous, 1928-1947 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - M, Miscellaneous, 1931-1942 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Mailing lists, 1927-1945 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Malinowski, Bronislaw, 1939 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Mead, Margaret, 1941-1945 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Mekeel, Scudder, 1941-1946 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Midland Authors, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Miner, Horace, 1938 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Moorehead, W. K., 1930-1937 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Moorehead, W.K.,1928-1930 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Murdock, George, 1939-1942 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - N, Miscellaneous, 1927-1942 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - N, Miscellaneous,1934-1947 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Nash, Philleo, 1936-1942 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Nash, Edith Rosenfels (includes field correspondence about Community Study of the Klamath Reservation,) 1936 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - National Geographic, 1936-1937, 1942 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - National Park Service, 1934-1936 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - National Research Council: General, 1929-1944 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - National Research Council: Mississippi Valley Archaeology, 1933-1936 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - National Research Council: Carl E. Guthe, 1930-1933 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - National Research Council: Carl E. Guthe, 1928-1936 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - National Research Council: Carl E. Guthe, 1928-1933 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - National Research Council: Carl E. Guthe, 1935-1946 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Nesbitt, Paul, 1929-1938 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Neumann, Georg, 1929-1942 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Neville, Russell, 1929-1935 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Newman, Marshall, 1935-1038 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - O, Miscellaneous, 1928-1944 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Oberg, Kalervo, 1930-1940 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Opler, M.E. (field correspondence about the Apache, 1933) (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Osgood, Cornelius, 1929-1945 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - P, Miscellaneous, 1938-1946 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Pacific Relations (American Council Institute of Pacific Relations, Inc.), 1944 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Paul, Benjamin (including field correspondence from Guatemala, 1941), 1939-1941 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Payne, E. W., 1932 (Box 12, Folder 3)